that has happened since.
Right. Perfect. So, uh again for those
of you who are on the video,
uh
welcome again to this last lecture of uh
IDL spring 2026. This today's lecture is
on Boltzman machines. Quick recap. Bzman
machines are extensions of Hopfield
networks. We saw in the last class that
Hopfield networks were what won
Jeffenton and uh John Hopfield
you know they're very aonomously named
uh their Nobel prize in physics in 2024.
What was a Hopfield network? It was this
symmetric loopy network where every the
output of every neuron went to every
other neuron
and uh so anytime the neuron was
activated the network was activated from
an initial state it would evolve the
activations of the individual neurons
are threshold activations which took the
value of either one or minus one
depending on whether the field which is
the aphine term at the neuron was
positive or not.
So the story so far, the Hopfield
network is a loopy binary network with
symmetric connections. Every neuron
attempts to align itself with the sign
of the weighted combination of the
outputs of other neurons, the field at
the neuron. Given an initial
configuration, the neurons begin to flip
to align themselves in this manner,
causing the field at other neurons to
change, potentially making them flip.
And each evolution of the network in
this manner is guaranteed to decrease a
notion of energy that we defined
analogously to the energy of physical
materials spin glasses. The energy is
lower bounded which means there's some
point below which the energy cannot go
and each flip of a neuron results in a
finite decrease in this energy which
means that the total number of flips is
bounded because each flip causes a very
quantifiable decrease in the energy. If
you add enough of these quantifications,
you're going to hit the floor.
And so we saw this little visual example
of how these things evolve.
We also saw that the network acts as a
content addressable memory. If you
design the network just right, then the
configurations at which the network
eventually
uh stabilizes. These are patterns that
are some sort of memory. These are
remembered patterns. So if you
initialize the network not too far from
one of these configurations, it's going
to evolve into these configurations.
So uh this is an instance of recalling a
memory based on partial recall rather
than address.
So we saw some examples in the last
class. If I designed a network to
remember the bugs bunny and the chip and
dale and then if I initialize the
network with either a noisy version of
the bugs bunny or a partial copy of the
chip and dale, it would evolve and uh
either clean out the pattern in the
first case or fill it out in the second
case.
But then we also saw that the network
must be designed to store desired
memories. And what does it mean for a
memory to be stored? The memory pattern
must be stationary.
Meaning if you start initialize the
network in that pattern, it should not
evolve because the field at every neuron
aligns with the current output exactly.
And it should be stable. Meaning if you
flip one of these neurons, it should go
back to this to the remembered pattern.
We also saw that network memory can be
trained by Hebian learning. And if
you're trying to remember only one
pattern then he learning basically says
that the weight between any two neurons
is simply the product of the values of
those two neurons. And uh that gives you
a stable stationary network for one
pattern. If you have more than one
pattern then you can just average the
heian networks for all of the target
patterns. But then we found that for a
network with n neurons you can store no
more than about.14
n patterns. And even so you have a 0.004
probability that some of these are going
to be not going to be remembered. And we
also saw why this was not the best uh
way to design the network. And that's
because it turns out that the Hebian
learning rule is basically just a
gradient descent rule where you're
trying to minimize the energy of the
target patterns but you're not think
considering the non-target patterns. So
those might end up being remembered as
well, right? And so the story continues
that the Hopfield network with n neurons
regardless of the manner in which you
store these patterns can store up to
order n patterns.
And uh we can train these networks
through optimization techniques that we
saw in the last class to remember a
specific set of patterns. But the number
of patterns that you can uh
intentionally remember is about is about
the same as the number of neurons in the
network itself. The network might end up
being stable at other patterns which are
not necessarily intended.
And that's because anytime you have some
subset of uh a local minima, you can
have other other local minima that just
happen to happen because of the way the
network is set up. Right?
So the memory capacity
number of patterns you can store
intentionally of an n bit network is
order n. Now suppose I have a
a th00and pixel image right your mnest
images are 768 pixels so th00and is good
enough for digits. I can store up to
maybe 1,000 images.
What if I want to store 2,000 images?
Obviously, there's more than there are
more than 1,000,000 pixel images that I
can create, right? If I want to store
2,000 images,
but the images themselves are just,000
pixels each. Now, we saw that the
network has to have the same number of
pixels as neurons as the number of
pixels. Right? Now, just putting your
engineer hat on, how would you design
and construct a network to store more
than 1,000 digits? Keeping in mind that
the number of digits that can be stored
is proportional to the number or is
roughly this the same as the number of
neurons in the network.
There are two things going on. The
number of digits that can be stored is
about the same as the number of neurons
in the network. But the number of
neurons in the network is the same as
the number of pixels in the image.
Right? So how do you construct a network
that can store more than 1,000 digits?
You're
thinking hats on
>> does have to be a bit
>> hur
Yeah. Yeah. They're all bits, right?
Yeah.
>> We can add more neurons.
>> We can add more neurons. And what will
those neurons have?
That's the correct answer. Right? So, I
can add a large number of neurons whose
values I don't care about. I know that
the image is a thousand pixels, right? I
can just append a bunch of another
another 1,000 arbitrary pixels to my
image, which I will ignore when I'm
trying to view the images. But now I
have 2,000 pixels, which means my neuron
network has 2,000 neurons, I can store
2,000 images,
right?
And so the new capacity if I just add k
neurons to my network is n plus k you
only care about the patterns and the
first n neurons. So these we these are
what we will call the visible neurons.
These are the ones we want to look at
and those are the hidden neurons. They
the carry all the uh extra bits that you
sort of slapped on just to increase the
capacity of the network. Right? And so
here's the terminology. The neurons that
store the actual patterns are visible
neurons. The neurons that only serve to
increase the capacity but whose patterns
we are not really interested in are what
we will call the hidden neurons. They
can be set to anything because you're
never going to visualize them. Right?
But then is it any odd thing or is there
something smart something smart you can
do? Now if I just have n pixels and if I
have n neurons then the maximum number
of p patterns I can store is bounded by
the width n again just to reiterate
right so I'm going to pad this with k ne
k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k
k bit bits
and now because each bit is going to be
stored by one neuron, I have an n plus k
bit network and so we can store n plus k
p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p
p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p
patterns,
but then what do we keep? what do we
store and the remaining k bits because
obviously you're not going to be
visualizing them but what they contain
matters right because they are part of
the energy contour they're being
considered in the energy contour so
simple option I just randomly fill them
in I just make and this would work so
for every image that I store I append
another thousand bits and I fill them in
with some random pattern and now I have
a 2,000 bit pattern I can try to
construct a network to store these. And
I can store 2,00 images, right? Uh, and
how do I store them? Just the standard
optimization that we just saw.
So, how do I retrieve a memory? Huh? I
can do the usual thing. I'm I can just
initialize the network the the network
with some some variant of this pattern.
Let it evolve. But when I do so, I'm not
exploiting something very,
you know, something that I could easily
exploit. What would that be in this
setting?
If I just use the standard technique for
retrieval and stand fill up the bits
randomly, what am I not exploiting?
>> The fact that you don't care about the
bits.
>> The fact that I don't care about the
remaining bits, right? That can be
exploited, right? So, here's a poll for
those of you who are we still have polls
even if it's the last class of the
semester.
Okay, what are the answers
um for the first question?
I had the second point and the third
point or the second question
um the appending k relevant bits and the
last question
um no
>> right exactly right you can store order
end patterns they can be trained using
gradient descent by appending k relevant
bits you can increase the capacity of
the network what we can exploit is that
it is not important for us to remember
the recall all those k bits exactly
right that that ought to help. So
again the value taken by the k hidden
neurons during recall doesn't really
matter. So when you recall it so long as
the first n bits the visible bits are
correctly recalled you don't mind you
don't care about making mistakes and the
remaining bits right that's one. Second,
there's no need for me to if I'm just
extending my visible pattern with a
bunch of random bits. There's no need
for me to just create one pattern,
right? I can take a digit and I can
create many copies of which of it, each
of which is different, and I can store
them all, which means that I can
actually make the recall much more
robust because there many different
variants, all of which are going to end
up giving me the same visible patterns.
So these are things I could exploit
but then the problem becomes what do I
fill those things with and how do I
store them so that my capac capability
to remember is maximized
so
spotlight all right so a simple random
setting of the don't care bits
using the usual training and recall
strategies should work but it doesn't
sufficient iently exploit the redundancy
of the don't care bits. So it's possible
to set the don't care bits so that the
overall pattern and hence the visible
bits are in some sense more memorable
right
and uh also we can have multiple don't
care patterns for the target pattern. So
which means you get multiple valleys all
of which in your energy contour all of
which represent the same uh visible
pattern to exploit this properly exploit
the fact that those don't care bits
don't matter and so you can have
redundancy in the don't care bits so
long as the visible bits are properly
stored. Uh we need to figure out how to
fill those guys up. There are many
strategies you can think of. we can do
it randomly etc. But it turns out the
smartest way to do to go about it is to
think about the whole thing as a
probabilistic machine. This is the
second half. The first half of the last
class was why John Hopfield won his
Nobel. Today's class was why Jeff Henton
won his Nobel.
Right.
So let's return to physics.
But did last class make sense to all of
you guys? Do you think you can go off
and win a Nobel? It's 1984.
>> Yes. No.
>> Made sense. I know about the Nobel.
>> Okay. You can. Right. You know, you have
enough to go off and win Nobel. Right.
Okay. Right. Now, uh so let's
return to the behavior of the Hopfield
network and its analogy to spin glasses.
Spin glasses are characterized by a
Boseman distribution. How many of you
have heard of the term absolute zero?
You've done physics, right? What's
absolute zero?
>> 0 Kelvin.
>> What's 0 Kelvin? What happens at 0
Kelvin?
>> Particles stop moving.
>> Nothing moves. 0 Kelvin is where the
universe just comes to an absolute
standill. Right. What happens above 0
Kelvin?
>> Above.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Particles start to vibrate or move.
Right? So, if I'm thinking of a spin
glass where I have all of these dipoles
and they're all trying to align
themselves with the field,
what would you think happens to all of
these dipoles above absolute zero? Are
they just going to come to a stable
configuration and stay
or is there going to be some motion?
>> Physics says it's there's got to be some
motion, right? Otherwise, they would be
at absolute zero. That object would be
at absolute zero, right? The objects are
not at absolute zero. So what really
happens?
The system is not actually in a specific
state at any time. What happens is that
the system thanks to having thermal
energy, they're not at absolute zero.
The things keep bouncing around.
The state keeps changing. What changes?
What h what what really happens is that
there is a probability distribution over
the states. Meaning all of the dipoles
can point in different directions. You
have different configurations. They keep
flipping between these. But there's a
probability distribution with which they
flip between these states.
And again, if I just heat up an object
and maintain the temperature of the ob
of the of the object, but I let it stay,
does it still release heat?
What does your physics tell you?
I heat this up
to, you know, 100°
and then I keep it at 100°. Will this be
releasing heat?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. But the temperature hasn't changed.
Why does that happen?
>> There's also heat.
>> Mhm.
>> Because there's also heat input.
>> There's heat in here. Right. So what
this guy
somewhere here there's a chalk. I know
there's a chalk. Yeah.
At any state remember when I'm speaking
of a state it's like + one + one minus1
minus1. So each of these particles has
some state some value orientation. So
there's a state right? associated with
any state we said there was an energy
this is the potential energy of the
state right
and what was the energy of the state if
I it's half
y transpose w y where w is basically the
set of interactions and you can have an
you could have an external field
y
if b was the external field right but
that's the energy of one state if the
system is bouncing around between
states.
How do you characterize the energy of
the entire mass?
How would you characterize it?
H
you know the answer.
>> Expected value.
>> Expected value. Thank you. Right. So I'm
going to have the actual energy is the
probability that it's going to be in any
state times the energy of the state
summation over all states. That's the
expected value. That's the overall
capacity of the system to do work.
Right? What happens when you just let a
system be? Does it stay at that state in
state or does it keep going to lower
energy states? What does physics tell
you?
keeps going to lower energy states which
means the probability distribution is
going to keep shifting towards what
kinds of states?
>> Going to keep shifting with states
towards with lower energy in the limit.
Where would you stop?
You know the answer.
>> Whatever the minimum
>> you would stop at the lowest energy
state, right? That's where you would
stop. But is that does that really is
that really what happens when I leave
something on at non zero? No. Right? We
know it keeps bouncing. So why doesn't
it just go down to the lowest energy
state and stay there?
Why?
There's energy being added into the
system somehow.
>> You heard the terms entropy.
What is entropy?
It's like uh the tendency to go towards
like randomness
>> tendency to go towards randomness and
how does that relate? So you know this
is the concept of entropy comes from
thermodynamics from physics right so
this the internal energy of the system
representing the capacity to do work is
the expected energy over all states if
you just let it be. So this is how much
energy you could potentially harness to
do external work. But
if you just let the system be there's
internal disorder in the system which is
that's where Bsman's constant comes in
and that's where the formula for entropy
comes in right minus K * P log P. And so
the actual Helmho's free energy what you
can harness from the system is this guy
expected value of the energies minus
whatever you can lose because of the
internal disorder in the system when
it's at a particular temperature there's
something that system is in disorder
it's not going to stay still static
right and so the system is going to cool
what would it cool will it cool the
internal energy or this Or is it going
to be this star?
What is going to be reduced?
If you just let the system be, what does
physics tell you?
Come on, guys. So, what you know the
answer?
>> Just the internal energy.
>> No, it's going to actually reduce this
Helmhold's free energy, right? When you
let the system be, it's going to keep
losing heat,
but it can't go all the way down to the
lowest energy state. that's counteracted
by this the disorder and so the disorder
is basically this term over here minus P
log P that's the entropy multiplied by
Bsman constant and it depends again on
the temperature the higher the
temperature is the greater the disorder
right and so this entire Helmhold's free
energy is what is going to be reduced by
the system as a system just stays there
a system held at a specific temperature
unease by varying the rate at which it
visits the various states
to reduce the free energy in the system
until a specific minimum free energy has
been achieved. And at that point of time
the probability distribution with which
the various states are uh uh visited.
That's the Bman distribution. This
making sense to everybody?
Right? You're halfway to analog guys.
Okay. So and how do I find this
distribution? I can just differentiate
it and equate it to zero. So when I
differentiate this uh again the
probabilities must sum to uh one. So I'm
going to have to add this leng over here
which says lambda summation p minus one.
And then if I differentiate it there I'm
trying to estimate the probabilities the
pt of s right. So if I try to
differentiate this with respect to those
terms the derivative with respect to any
pts that first guys is going to give me
e of s the second time second term
there's the key kt outside there should
be an uppercase t uh the derivative of p
log p is 1 + log p right and then uh uh
plus lambda equals 0. solve for the
whole thing. You just end up with this
formula over here where it says that the
probability of any state is proportional
to the exponent of the negative of the
energy of the state divided by the Bzman
constant time t. So you can see that
the lower the energy, the higher the
probability of the state. Exponentially
higher and the higher the energy, the
lower the probability of the state. But
every state is going to have a non-zero
probability. It's only at absolute zero
where t becomes zero that only the most
the lowest energy state remains. Once t
just nudges off of zero, the other
states begin to become increasingly
possible. And if t is infinity all
states are equally possible right there
is no favored state. This making state
sense to all of you guys. And so this is
also the lrangian is to make sure that
the probabilities sum to one. Right? So
this is also known as the gibbs
distribution. The one over z outside is
a normalizing constant to make sure the
whole thing is a probability
distribution. Note the dependence on t.
At t equals0 the system always rem
remains in the lowest energy
configuration of p1. Right? And so this
is the bsman distribution. When I just
set up the spin glass at some
temperature uh the uh every state has a
has has an internal uh has an energy
associated with it and the system uh is
going to sort of evolve. The temperature
also introduces native
uh uncertainty right disorder and so the
system evolves so that this it keeps
releasing energy in the form of heat
until this term the the helmhold energy
is minimized at which point the system
the probability with which the system is
in the various states is the boltsman
distribution this is what we're going to
emulate this making sense to everybody
that's why we call them boldsman
machines Okay. So the system
probabilistically se select states with
lower energy.
And what is analing?
So remember when anytime you uh
construct some material that is supposed
to have crystal structure or some kind
of contained structure if you just make
it and let it cool you know rapidly it
develops cracks. It develop falls. These
things become brittle. Right? So the
standard procedure is to anneal it. You
heat it and you then you let it cool
very slowly, you keep decreasing the
temperature. And the reason you do this,
you know, slowly is that in that
process, if you do, if you did it
infinite decimally slowly, then you're
guaranteed that it's going to end up in
the lowest energy configuration when you
get to absolute zero. But if you do it
or if you do it slowly enough, then this
the probability distribution over the
states is going to favor low energy
states. But if you do it rapidly, you're
going to end up in a local minima where
higher energy states might actually end
up having a sufficiently high
probability that
you know the system actually favors
those and higher energy states are where
the system is likely to break.
So uh so the system probabilistically
selects states with lower energy. If you
cool it, if you let the temperature go
down very slowly, eventually it's going
to arrive at the global minimum state.
will have the
uh state with the lowest energy very
very high probability. So here's the
second call.
Maybe guys on Zoom can answer this.
What's the answer to the first question?
Zoom.
Do we have an answer?
Anyone on Zoom answering it? No. Okay.
One of you guys, what's the answer to
the first question?
H.
What about the second one?
>> The third.
>> Okay, let's see. Right. The hotfield
network is a computational analog of the
deterministic federal material material.
The true behavior of thermodynamic
systems we are stoastic.
And so Hawkfields can be modified to
emulate the stoastic behavior of
thermodynamic systems which is what
we're going to do right again. So we're
going to have this energy associated
with the property network. And now I can
define a probability distribution over
the states of the network just like at
the spin glass has a probability
distribution over states and say that
the prob the system is in one of these
states with the probability that's
proportional to e ra to the minus minus
of the energy of the system in that
state. Again the uh it's a probability
distribution. So all over all possible
states the probabilities must sum to
one. So the actual probability
distribution ends up with this
denominator term which is the sum of the
numerator over all possible states
summation over all possible states of e
ra to minus energy of the state. Right?
And this so this is the probability that
the system is going to be in any given
state where the energy of course is what
we saw earlier uh minus summation
wig jbi
si j minus psi right I haven't got the
half over there because I have i less
than j otherwise I need to I'd have to
put in the half okay
so
if I let this and if I let the system
evolve according to this probability
distribution eventually it's going to
settle down in is going to say a
configuration where it visits the
various states according to this
distribution
which is the bsman distribution. So this
is what I'll call a stochastic hotfield
network. It's a stochastic hopfield
network models a probability
distribution where the actual
probability distribution that it models
is the boltsman distribution. the state
is a boundary string and of course the
parameters of the model are the weights
of the network right
and so
the pro if I sample the system at any
time the probability that it's going to
be in any given state S is simply P of S
which is given by this Bsman
distribution which means that the system
is actually a generative model it
generates samples according to the Bsman
distribution this way back when in 80s
was the first generative model uh
composed by neural networks. So you can
see the importance of it right and well
what does it mean to make the system
evolve in a stochastic manner it's one
thing to say this you know in theory I
want it to evolve in this manner how do
you implement it in practice so what is
the stochastic problem how does the
stoastic network evolve what is the rule
by which the neurons flip and this is
where it gets really great right so
you find that it This collapses to
something that we are very very familiar
with.
Let's consider a state S where the
values are + one + one + one + one and +
one. What is the
and this is state S and this is a state
S prime. Focus on this guy.
+ one + one minus one + one and + one.
So these two differ in only one bit
right.
So given the rest of these guys if I fix
the rest of these guys. So let me call
this the remaining bits. Right? So P of
S given R plus P of S prime given R is
going to be one. Right? I fixed the R.
only one bit is allowed to change. So
the bit can either take the value + one
or it can take the value minus one.
Right? So what is log of
P of S? That's going to be P of R
log of P of R
plus log of
P of S given R. Right? log of
P of S prime is also going to be log of
P of R
plus log of P of S prime R. This is just
base rule. Right? The difference between
the two log of P of S minus log of
P of R is simply going to be log of P of
S given R
minus log of P of S prime given R.
Everybody with me so far? Nothing fancy,
right?
the terminal that we p
s.
So you're with me so far, right?
And which is simply log of e of s given
r
/
1 - p of s given, right? Because log of
a minus log of b is log of a / b. And
you know P of S prime given R as we saw
is simply
1 - P of S given R. So we have this at
the bottom. Log what is log of P of what
is log of
P of S given R. R is given right. So
this is going to be the energy
contribution minus the energy of all the
bits in R
whatever it is
right
uh actually what is log of P of S is the
energy of all the bits in R
plus
or rather minus the summation over J. So
you're considering just the iat bit,
right? It's
iig
SG. That's all you're going to get.
This is the one bit that you're
considering, right? This term is the
contribution for the energy of this one
bit.
Okay. Why am I writing just SG and not
writing SI? Because SI is + one.
Okay. So also I can say log of
ef prime is going to be minus energy of
r
plus summation wig j
why plus because in this case it is
+ one right minus one
so I can just write those two and
there's a half of course right so it
turns out that if I take log of p of S
minus log of P of S prime that simply
becomes the summation W
SJ plus BJ I'm also adding the bias this
making sense to everybody
right so this is really beautiful why
because I say log of P divided by 1 - P
is summation W this aine term
exponentiating both sides I'm going to
get
P = 1 - p * e to the aine term. Shift
things around and it turns out that the
probability of one for this bit is
simply is it formula familiar?
This guy here.
What is this?
Has given you the answer. Right? There's
a sigmoid. That's where the sigmoid came
from. It didn't drop out of the sky.
It said what is the probability of a
specific neuron taking the value one
if the rest of the state of the rest of
the neurons is fixed in a Bsman machine
and it turns out that's a segment right
and so here we are right
regular network is a stoastic machine
each neuron is now a stoastic unit with
a binary state which can take value 0 or
one with a probability that depends only
on the local field is 1 / 1 + e to - z.
This making sense to everybody,
right? And this is and you also see
where the sigmoid actually came from.
Why that particular formula and not
anything else? It just falls up
literally here. Spin glasses. This was
this was very important work. You have
to work hard for this notebook. Okay.
And so uh the hopfield network is a
probability distribution of a binary
sequences. This is the Boltsman
distribution. The conditional
distribution of individual bits, right?
This
P of S given R is simply the probability
of this bit because the rest of the bits
are fixed,
right? So the conditional distribution
of any given bit is just a sigmoid.
And so how can this network evolve
stochastically? Very simple. I'm going
to cycle through the neurons. At each
neuron, I compute the probability that
that neuron takes the value one using
the sigmoid and then I can flip a bias
coin. I can sample from that sigmoid
and uh set the neuron itself. That make
sense to everybody what we just did,
right? And so and I keep doing this
after many after many iterations the uh
whole thing is going to stabilize to a
Bzman distribution. So evolution of the
network assuming t= 1. I initialize the
network in some pattern. Then I cycle
through the neurons. At each neuron I
compute the sigmoid at the neuron and
then I sample the output of the neuron
from that sigmoid and I set the neuron
according to that probability according
to whatever value has been drawn from
this distribution. I keep doing this.
When do we stop? What is the final state
of the system? Is the system ever going
to be in a static state?
No, it's stochastic, right? It's a spin
glass. So, how do you determine what the
final state of the system is? If I'm
trying to recall a picture, what would
you do?
>> Minimize the expected value of the
stoastic system.
>> It's going to evolve for a long time.
And so, you know, the probability is
going to the energy keeps going down
expected energy and then eventually it's
going to stabilize at some distribution.
It's going to continue evolving, right?
There's no static picture. So what we
what is so how do you recall a memory
once you've evolved enough you see okay
here I've sort of hit stability and then
I continue letting the system evolve but
I know that at this point it's actually
evolving according to the Boseman
distribution because the rest of it is
done right it's stabilized I can sample
it over many steps and then take the
average over all of the steps and that's
going to give my give me my final
configuration best the expected
configuration which is exactly what you
said right make sense Everybody
right? Okay. So,
selecting this is the Boseman machine.
Selecting the next state is analogous to
drawing a sample from the Boseman
distribution at t= 1 in a universe where
the Boseman constant is also one. It's
similar to the energy landscape of the
spin glass model. You know this is a
2009 paper. So, anything that has low
energy has exponentially higher
probability, right? And you can also
introduce so if you want to perform
noisy pattern completion you just
initialize the entire network where the
network evolve. If you want to uh do a
partial pattern completion we saw two
different examples. One where I give you
the noise a noisy version of the data
and it cleans it up. The other where I
give you a partial recall and it fills
it out. In both cases you're just going
to be doing the same thing. But if I
have a partial pattern let's say I'm
giving you the upper portion of a
picture. I wanted to fill out the lower
picture portion of the picture. Then I'm
going to fix the bits that I'm already
I'm certain about, right? Because this
is the upper portion of the picture and
I let only the bits corresponding to the
lower portion of the picture evolve and
then read it off. Whereas if I've got a
noisy picture, I let every bit evolve
and read it off. That make sense? You
see the difference between the two
situations? Okay.
I can also introduce a temperature term
like in physics. Instead of saying just
Z equals the weighted sum of all of the
other neurons, I can have a 1 / T, I can
initially set T to be a large value and
then I can keep cooling it reducing it
over steps. This is what they call
analing. And so at t= infinity, the
energy surface will be flat. At t= 1,
it's the usual energy surface. At t
equals0, this becomes a hop field
network
because you're always picking the lowest
energy configuration. It's not
stochastic,
right? And so this field the field
quantifies the energy difference
obtained by flipping the bit. If the
difference is not large,
the probability of the bit being either
zero or one approaches.5
and t is a temperature parameter.
Increasing it moves it towards moves the
bits towards 0.5. As t is in t is
infinity then + 1 and minus one and zero
are equally probable.
At t= 1 you get the traditional
definition of field and energy. At t
equals z you end up with a half field
network.
All of this making sense to you guys?
Okay. So
are you ready? you keep you instead of
just having a fixed value of t, what you
could do is start off with a very large
value of t and then keep decreasing the
t all the way to zero. And even in the
most complicated energy landscape, this
is guaranteed in theory to actually find
you the uh lowest energy configuration.
So this is actually also the the basis
of simulated analing if those of those
of you who heard of it. Uh simulated
analing is was the original papers by
Metropolis and Hastings back in the
1950s in a chemical engineering journal.
But it really became popular after uh we
saw that even in a Bsman machine
framework you can use the same setup.
You can you're basically drawing upon
principles from physics
to find the lowest energy of the
configuration or uh the uh minimum value
of an objective function.
So this network keeps evolving. When do
we stop? We stop when we can always
compute the overall probability of the
network. Right? And if the expected
value of this energy
uh the the probability of the
configuration
doesn't keep increasing the on point,
then you can stop. And what is the final
state of the system? Again, remember
that when the when the network is very
noisy, it's likely to visit all states
equally. So the probability of every
state is very small. When the network is
very stable, then it's going to visit
the high probability states much more
frequently than it's going to visit the
low probability states. So evolution
increases the expected
log probability of the states that
you're visiting, right? they can do and
uh
to recall we just saw you can recall
anyway. So here's the recap. Stochastic
hot networks the probability of each
neuron is given by conditional
distribution.
What is the probability of the entire
set of neurons taking a configuration Y
again right for any given configuration
the probability is just proportional to
E RA to minus the energy of the
configuration divided by T. Okay.
And so you stop when the running average
the lock probability of the current
stops increasing
or the energy the running average of the
energy stops decreasing. And of course,
you read things as the average. Okay,
there's a problem here.
Did all of this make sense, guys?
There was a lot of math, but wasn't
really hard.
Okay, someone on Zoom if you want to
answer both questions.
Someone on Zoom.
True.
>> True. And what about the second one?
Also true. Right. Right. So the stoastic
halffield network flips neurons
according to a probability distribution
computed by logistic activation. I can
flip a neuron even if doing so increases
the energy of the configuration.
Tired.
You want to go wash your face or
something? I can wait for you.
So any questions so far?
No.
How? Okay. We just made something that
was nice and deterministic. The Hawfield
network which was so easy to understand
that you derived the entire math
yourselves, right? We made that
probabilistic. How much more complicated
do you think this is going to make math?
Do you mind turning the phone upside
down there?
Flip the phone please. Turn it upside
down. Thank you.
Can you come up front? I guess the room
is too dark. Come up here. Yes.
So,
how much more complex do you think this
makes the map?
>> What is your expectation?
>> I think we'll be pretty elegant.
What if I told you that the the learning
rules will not change at all?
No, that's it is elegant, but the true
elegance arises from the fact that
nothing changes.
All that changes is that during
inference, you're actually
randomly sampling as opposed to
deterministically changing things. But
during training, nothing changes. And
I'm going to prove this. Okay. So here
is the opal network. It's a probability
distribution over binary sequences.
Correct. Uh the probability of any
configuration is e ra to minus the
energy of the configuration proportional
to this. This is the conditional
distribution of individual bits. So the
conditional distribution of individual
bits is a the logistic. We're going to
call this a banish. Right? Now for now
this is a probabilistic machine. How do
we train generative models? How do we
train probabilistic networks? What is
the objective that we use? Anyone
remember?
You have a collection of training data.
How do you train these models?
>> Likelihood.
>> You maximize the training data
probability that maximize the log
likelihood of the training data, right?
You perform maximum likelihood training.
And so that's what would make sense even
over here, right?
So how does the probabilistic view
affect our train model? Not much.
First let's go back to the half network
itself. In the case of the half network
that's what we had. We minimize the
energy of the target patterns. We
maximize the total energy of all the
non-target patterns. Right? And when you
difference when you differentiated it
with respect to parameters, the
derivative you got was basically the the
u
standard heavian rule over all the
training target patterns minus the
heavian rule over non-target patterns.
You can have a weighted combination. You
know if some patterns are more important
than others or if some patterns are
repeated in your training data so that
alpha just tells you how frequently each
of the patterns is being shown, right?
and uh on in the first summation and the
beta in the second summation is
basically showing you exactly again how
the relative importance of each of those
and these look like expectations right
this is your heavy row this is what
you're going to end up with okay
so
what the first term over here is
basically the expected value of the
outer product of your patterns of your
states is when the samples are drawn
from the distribution you're trying to
learn.
Right? That's what it looks like. I have
a bunch of training data points which
means I've sampled these from the
distribution that I'm trying to love. So
this first term is just an expectation
over
the distribution you are trying to learn
which is not necessarily a BSman
distribution can be anything. If I look
at the distribution of all images, is
that going to be a BSman machine? It's
not going to be a BSman. It's not going
to be a BSman distribution. Who knows
what it's going to be, right? So the
samples are being drawn from the actual
distribution of the data. The contracts
term, the second term, which is what you
use to make sure that the rest of the
patterns are not remembered. the
patterns that you're not interested in,
you have no idea what the distribution
is, but the natural distribution for
these patterns is the BSman distribution
in this framework. And so the
probability distribution for those guys,
the ones that you sample from, is going
to be the BSman distribution. Once you
understand this, I don't need to do the
rest of the lecture, but I'm going to do
it anyways. Right? So this makes sense
to all of you guys. It's just natural,
right? It makes sense. But let's derive
it.
So you must learn the weights to
remember the target states and destroy
other states.
That's in a half network. In a training
a bull machine, you must learn the
weights to assign a desired probability
distribution to the states that you have
observed
vectors y. I'm just going to call that s
because I had two messy notations and
I'm too lazy to change the notation. And
uh we should assign more probability
probability to patterns we like and less
to the ones that we don't like. Right?
So here we are. I'm given a set of
training patterns. These are all the
images that I'm who that I'm trying to
memorize for instance. Right? And uh uh
if I give you a collection of images, if
I give you a collection, if if you see a
lot more twos than you see nines, then
you want to have a much assign a higher
probability to twos, you must make less
error. When you recall a two than when
you recall a nine because nines are
infrequent. If you make errors in nines,
you probably are not going to encounter
it at all. Right? So that must naturally
be factored in.
And so we want to assign low probability
to patterns that are not seen at all
seen that are less frequent. And ideally
you want to assign zero probability to
patterns
that never happened or at least
something that's very small. Right?
So you want to maximize the likelihood
of what you have observed
there on top.
Again if you look at this probability
over here P of S the numerator is E
raised to the energy of the state minus
of the energy of the state right the
denominator is the same thing as the
numerator summed over all states if I
take the log of this guy the numerator
is going to first the the numerator is
simply going to give you the energy time
summation I ji
the denominator is going to give you log
of the summation over all states
of e to whatever. Right? So, is this
making sense?
The term on top, right? And if I average
this over all of my training data, then
this is 1 / n summation over all of my
training samples of the term to the
right.
This making sense, right? That first
term is just the same thing as the
energy term that you saw in your half
network.
The second term is the crazy one. Right?
making sense? And so when I
differentiate it, here's what is going
to happen. The first term, the
derivative is simply going to be 1 / n
summation sisj.
This is exactly the same as the uh
heavier learning term that you got for
hop networks. The question is what is
this second term? Because I have this
really crazy summation log of a
summation of an exponent, right? So what
happens when I differentiate it? So for
this I'm going to ask you this guy here.
Let's actually work this out.
First we have P of S is E R - energy of
S divided by summation S prime E -
energy of S.
Keep this in mind. Right. I'm trying to
differentiate. What is that? Log of
x of is it
summation
s prime
x of
term inside is summation i less than j
wig sj.
If I differentiate this with respect to
any wig, what am I going to what's the
derivative going to be? What's the first
thing that happens?
Calculus
like middle school calculus or high
school calculus, you should be able to
tell tell me the answer. What happens?
What is the derivative of log of y with
respect to y? First, what is that?
>> 1 / y right suppose it's y of x and I do
this with respect to x then what do you
get
>> 1 / yx * derivative of
>> y of x with respect to x right
let's take that over here
so the first thing you're going to get
is 1 / summation s prime e ra to
this is energy of respect
a release. Okay, minus the second term
is this guy.
What is the derivative of E to Y with
respect to Y?
>> Ey, right? What is the derivative of E R
Y of X with respect to X
times prime of X? This is y * d y / dx.
Right? I stick that over here. What is
that going to be?
Um s i s.
Firstly, you're going to get an exponent
of
i. Let's call this p of s.
That's the first one x i s. Is this
making sense? What is this here?
What is that?
looking what's looking like that. Look
at this guy is the same as this term,
right?
So this is simply E of S X I SG.
Make sense to everybody? And so here you
have it, right? It just comes out
to be the derivative of the second term
is the summation over all states of P of
S prime SID for that state. What is
that? That's the expectation,
right? That's the expectation over
or over the BS man distribution.
Beautiful, huh? And so the second term
is simply the expected value of xd all
possible values of the state under the
bman distribution. But you cannot
compute it exhaustively because there
are an exponential number of these
states. So when that happens, what do we
do?
>> Sample.
>> Sample. Thank you. Right. And so guys,
okay, you're getting that.
You're going through 10 years of
research in 30 minutes. And you're being
pretty good at it, right? So the
expectation can be estimated as the
average of samples drawn from the
distribution. How do you s draw samples
from this BSman distribution? It's a
BSAN distribution. How would you draw
samples from it?
You run the network, right? If you run
the network, it's going to give you a
sample from the distribution. You
initialize the network randomly.
You let it evolve
and then
read the values of the samples. These
are what I'm going to calling calling
simulated values. And so the overall
training is going to be the second term.
I'm going to run the network a whole
bunch of times. I get a collected
collection of simulated values. I take
the average of SIS over all of the
simulated values. That's my second term,
right? And so
there is my overall der of log of P of S
with respect to WIG
uh log of the training data. Log of the
probability of the training data. This
looks like your Bsman your Hfield
network, right?
You're drawing samples.
You can't go over all possible
states. So you're letting it run
according to the Boseman distribution.
Then you're draw then you're reading
samples from it and you're taking the
average over the samples as a second
term. The first term is simply the
standard heavy rule. Okay. And so that's
going to be the overall training. Let it
initialize the works weights. Let the
network run to obtain simulated state
samples. Compute gradient and update.
Right. Beautiful.
But this is very similar to what you did
in the offfield network. So can you give
me all the usual shortcuts?
Do I need to pull up the network
everywhere?
No. Right. So where do I need to pull it
up?
>> The uh minima that you
>> the minima adjacent to the target
values, right? Or maybe just the
immediate neighborhood. So which means
that I don't need to run the simulation
randomly.
I can just start with the values that
I'm trying to remember.
Let the network evolve except that you
know in the last class we let it evolve
deterministically. Now you're going to
flip a coin.
Then you let the network evolve
otherwise nothing else change.
Literally the only difference between
the last class and this is that I spent
40 minutes telling you to flip a coin,
right? 1 hour. That make sense to
everybody?
And so
how many of you find this to be
beautiful? I do. That we went through
all this math and arrived with the same
answer as before with the one difference
being you flipped a coin and you flipped
a coin according to a logistic a sigmoid
that we also familiar with right but
this is just the standard Hopfield
network. We have still not spoken about
increasing the capacity of the network
itself. Why did we say we're going to
increase the capacity of the network?
>> Add more stuff, right? Just add a bunch
of neurons. Add a whole bunch of neurons
whose actual values you don't care
about.
How would this change the map?
Remember those neurons
don't have an assigned value.
So without working through the math,
knowing what you do so far, if I asked
you to engineer a solution, what would
you do? But I'm trying to remember a
pattern. I have to remember even the
unseen bits, right? The hidden bits. How
would you engineer this?
>> You have the answer.
What I would do is add a bunch of copies
of what I want to remember with like
randomized
>> randomized half
>> k neurons.
>> Randomized half.
>> What is the probability distribution of
the unseen neurons? Remember these guys
are not part of your target pattern.
>> The target pattern has a distribution.
What about the unseen guys?
>> BSman distribution. So now how are you
going to fill those guys?
>> You're going to sample the BSman
distribution. You're going to fix the
fixed visible guys. You run the network
over the unseen guys,
right?
Do you need math to prove this?
Let's see it. Right.
Okay. So, the new capacity is n plus k.
We only care about the patterns of the
first 10 neurons because we're
interested in n bit patterns.
So, the neurons that store the actual
patterns are these visible bits.
The neurons have only served and
increase the capacity, but those actual
values are not important neurons. These
can be set to meet anything in order to
store a visible pattern. We're going to
use maximum likelihood estimation. And
you're taking the fact that things you
don't know have a rules map
distribution. Things that you can
observe have a distribution of their
own. Right? So
for a given pattern of visible neurons,
there are any number of paths. Which do
we choose?
You want to ideally you want to choose
something that results in the lowest
energy for the overall pattern but it's
an exponential search space. So you
assign a Bman distribution and you let
the model figure it out right.
So also you could have multiple patterns
right coupled with any visible pattern.
These would be stored these would be
multiple stored patterns that all give
the same visible output. How many do we
permit? Do I need to specify a pattern
or can I just use all of them? What I
mean by this is that we can work in
expectations. Right? So
uh again this is the basic framework
that we saw without hidden units. I'm
going to extend it to have hidden units.
The complete state pattern for even the
training patterns is unknown because the
hidden bits are not known since they
only patterns are only stored defined
over the visible units. We're going to
use what you guys just told me, right?
The probability. So for any pattern S, S
S has
two components which is the visible base
and the hidden base, right? And then I
have the probability distribution for
the visible bits which is what you get
from the real.
Then I have the probability distribution
for the
P of X
probability distribution for the hidden
bits
given the visible bits and this
is the world the universe this is a
BSman distribution this is what we're
going to be taking advantage of okay
and so
just
this is the Bman distribution that you
have over there the second term right
uh not here. So if I just want to
compute only the P of Ver
I'm using maximum estimation again.
So
P of V these are the resolution
of the hidden P of V comma H
just B rule right P of V comma H is
given by
H B which is the post distribution
right
and so uh that is I just written it out
explicitly over here
uh and so
log of P of V you don't have to worry
about the first term
skip the math it's getting late but if
you go through the exact same math that
we just did a little while ago it turns
are that your your update to is going to
end up looking like this. You're going
to be summing over
that should have been P of H given VS
here, right? PF H given V is the same as
PFS given V. It doesn't really matter.
Okay, because the visible bits are given
is the expectation over the BSman
distribution of the hidden states
of pro of the product of SI and SJ right
and so skipping the math because I know
you guys can do this I can just say
here is what happens
my network has two sets of states the
hidden states and the the visible states
and the hidden states
For every training pattern, I have to
fill it out to get the visible hidden
bits. So, I'm going to fix the hidden
bits. I'm going to let the I'm going to
fix the visible bits and I'm going to
let the hidden bits evolve according to
a BSman distribution and sample it. And
now I've got a completed
pattern.
I can do it multiple times if I so wish,
right? Or just once. And so every
training data instance now is no longer
partial. I have both the visible bits
and the hidden bits and I store the and
this becomes the pattern that I'm trying
to store. But of course the hidden bits
are going to depend on the current set
of current estimate for the weights. So
once I use these to update my
parameters, I'm going to have to go back
and redo the whole business of even
filling out the
uh hidden bits simply because the model
has changed. Right? So
the overall process is this. First,
you're going to do a Bsman distribution
over only the hidden bits. Then you're
going to do a BSman distribution over
the entire set of bits. So there's a
two-step process. You clamp the visible
bits. You let the Bsman distribution
over the hidden hidden bits evolve.
And that's going to give you a completed
pattern. Then you unclamp the visible
bits and let the whole thing evolve. And
that's going to give you a complete
pattern over
all the bits using a boltsman
distribution over all the bits. And so
these are uh
fix the visible bits
first
and fill out the hidden bits, then
unclamp the visible bits and let the
whole network involved.
And that's going to give you two
configurations. One where the visible
bits are fixed and only the hidden bits
have been constructed. one where the
empathing has been constructed then you
can use the standard heavy and rule
the difference between the product of
the bits
over these two samples as as as the
gradient that you're going to use to
update your parameters with that make
sense to everybody right even without
the math it's 10 minutes to the end of
the next semester so I'm sure you're not
dying for math are you dying for math
I'm not okay
but it makes sense
Right? It makes complete sense, right?
This is something that you could
actually build and you can be convinced.
And if I told you that there's a million
dollar prize 20 years down the line, you
could actually come up with the math
yourself.
So,
and so there's your
uh heavy. Okay.
Never find the home.
Okay. have the answers
>> uh for the first one the hidden neurons
and the second one um
true
>> okay so the irrelevant bits that we use
to extend the hawk network's capacity
correspond to the hidden neurons the
training paradigm of the B machine to
variant samples the hidden values to
complete hidden complete patterns right
and so these are just simple stochastic
extensions of our networks where the
primary novelty come came from the fact
that you added a bunch of extra bits to
increase the capacity of the network.
But then when you came up with this
bunch of extra bits, you needed a smart
way of filling out those bits. And it
turned out that the smart way of doing
it is to allow for the uh to make the
whole thing a probabilistic model. But
then there's a second reason for making
the whole thing hyper probability which
is this that if you look at the energy
contour pictures
uh we
have energy contours which look like
this
you know maybe there's a big rally and
then
something like that these happen all the
time right suppose you start over here.
Is this where you want to be or is this
where you want to be? Is this likely to
be a uh uh you know parasitic pattern or
is it something likely to be a real
memory that you want to remember?
What do you guys think? Probably just
noise, right? How do you make sure that
you're able to escape from that and get
into the big valley when you're trying
to recall a pattern?
If you're always using energy descent as
you do for the off field networks, you
are stuck over here.
So you want to have a probabilistic
mechanism which allows you to go up and
that's what the BSN machine framework
does. There's a nonzero probability that
you can go up here at which point you
have the ability to go down to the other
side which is the real one. So uh it has
this besides this this uh uh feature of
increasing the capacity of the network.
It also has an added feature that allows
you to escape local minima during
entrance time and to arrive at global
minima and your recall. Right?
So uh
skip on that you can do all of these
many slides. Okay.
You can also use Bullsman machines for
classification. How?
I can add bits
which are the class ID. Let's say you're
performing a classification between 100
classes. How many bits do I need to
remember to represent 100 classes?
>> 100.
>> No,
seven bits should do it right.
2 to 7.
Correct. I can actually increase
capacity by using more bits and having
some buffer like in error correction
code. And so I can actually represent my
class as bit patterns which I append to
my features.
And so now classification becomes
pattern completion
using a Bsman machine. Again that's
where using sigmoids for classification
came in back in the day in the 80s.
Right? So you can see how many different
beautiful things came out of this whole
model, right? Uh and uh
anyway, so one of the issues with BS and
machines is that training takes forever.
Why? Because when I let the network
evolve
and when I'm letting the entire network
evolve especially for the second term if
I have n neurons visible neurons and k
hidden neurons I have n + k² weights and
all of these things are going to be
contributing and the visible neurons
change the uh and because every neuron
talks to every other neuron the
evolution is very very slow. So can we
somehow make the thing more efficient?
This was the next big breakthrough. This
was uh restricted both machines which
said I'm going to partition the hidden
and the visible neurons so that the
hidden neurons don't talk to each other.
They only talk to the visible neurons.
And the visible neurons don't talk to
each other. They only talk to the hidden
neurons. Right? When I do this then when
I fix my visible neurons there is no
evolution. There's only one step of
changing the hidden neurons because
after that there is no way of changing
the hidden neurons themselves.
Right? And but then so for the first for
completing the pattern it's a singlestep
process instead of having a large
evolutionary process right for the
second one when I'm drawing a random
sample I still have to go through an
evolution but what I will have to do is
something of this kind right where
uh
I fix the visible neurons I sample the
hidden neurons then I use the sample
hidden neurons to update my visibles cuz
I desample my visible neurons. and go
through this process many times
and then out at the end at infinity
that's going to give me a sample from
the Bzman distribution over both the
hidden and visible neurons right it's
still expensive because I've got to do
this process many many many many times
but then there was the next uh so the
derivative that it ends up is going to
be simply the product of neuron values
in the first step minus the product of
neuron values in the last step the First
step is when you're just filling in the
pattern. The last step is when you're
unc, you know, you're treating the
entire thing as one large boltsman
machine. And that's where we realize
that you don't have to go all the way to
the end. You just have to pull up the
neighborhood of a pattern. And pulling
up the neighborhood of a pattern means I
can stop after just these three steps.
From the visible neurons, I update the
header neurons. I use the use those to
update the visible neurons, which I use
to update the header neurons. And now
those two guys, right? Those two the
edge in the first row and the edge in
the second row. Their their products are
the only ones I need to consider when
I'm updating my model. This makes the
whole thing very much more efficient. So
restricted Bsman machines were the way
to go for uh they remain the the favored
variant machines. Okay.
excellent generative models for binary
or binarized data. They can be all of
these have we've spoken about uh
networks where every neuron produced a
plus one or a minus one. It turns out
you can update those to extend those to
continuous value data exponential family
harmoniums
uh where you just append a Gaussian to
each neuron and so then they become
useful for both classification and
regression. then you have all kinds of
uh other extensions where you can just
make stack these things any number of
layers. So once uh Hinton came up with
the basic Paul Smolinsky came up with
the harmonium model the restricted Bsman
machine. Hinton came up with the Bsman
machine but then Hinton adopted the
restricted Bsman machine and he came up
with these other approaches but then you
never stop at a good thing right then
once you've invented something good you
have to make it complicated and
because that's what people do. So you
have all of these other models, sleep
poles and machines, host machines, wake
sleep algorithms. Uh they're in my
opinion not worth the time you spend
learning about it, but please don't
record this. Okay.
All right. And I missed a bunch of other
topics.
Learning and entrance over to machines,
RPMs, feature extractive models most
more structured deep words machines and
so on. So, how did these things actually
end up
changing the world?
It turns out that neural networks when
you went to 2010 or 2005, nobody was
using them. It's not that we didn't know
about them. It was just impossible to
train because regardless of what you
did, they ended up going into local
minima and giving you horrible
solutions. So around 2001 if your paper
title included neural networks in it
then new
lips neural information processing
systems would throw out any paper that
had neural in the title without review
right uh and so because things have
become so kind of ineffective
and then Hinton came up to this
realization that you can throw away the
labels and just train a restricted BSman
machine on the training data
like so
completely unsupervised and use the
weights that you have learned as the
initial weights to train your final
classifier and suddenly things that
never worked before began working. These
are amazing initial points and that's
the start of the latest
neural network revolution. Start off
around 2004 by 2010 everybody was using
neural networks. By 2015, you know, the
world had changed, right? After 40 years
of not making any progress, actually
after 140 years of not making any
progress with these models. So
that's uh that's the reason it's good to
know about these things. Anyway, we're
done.
Thank you for the class. One minute
over.
Enjoyed the course.
I try. I know your kids tried too, you
know, at least the ones who still turned
up in class. I'm good.
>> Thank you.
>> And I hope I didn't put you to sleep in
this final class.